Guide to the Whiffenpoofs, Yale University, Records
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Whiffenpoofs, Yale University, records
1904-2009
RU 156
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
28
(21 boxes, 3 folio folders)
The records consist of song arrangements, sheet music, audio recordings, membership lists, advertisements, clippings, photographs, posters, scrapbooks, and other memorabilia of the Yale Whiffenpoofs.
Whiffenpoofs (Musical group)
General note
Forms part of Yale Record Group 40 (YRG 40), Records of Yale clubs, societies, and organizations.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the records is partially restricted. See Collection Contents for details.
Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
Separated Materials
Recording of the 1950 Whiffenpoofs was transferred to the library"s Historical Sound Recordings collection.
Biographical / Historical
The Whiffenpoofs, a Yale student singing group, was founded in 1909 by four members of the University Quartet: George Pomeroy (1909), James M. Howard (1909), Meade Minnigerode (1910), Carl A. Lohmann (1910), and Denton Fowler (1909). The founders took their name from a fish story told by Joe Cawthorn, a popular comedian of the time. In a musical show called "Little Nemo," he described a fabulous creature which he caught by boring a hole in the lake and putting cheese around the hole. The Whiffenpoof, led on by the cheese, came up the hole, squawked, and then was caught. The Yale Whiffenpoofs claimed that they too could be led on by food and drink to squawk.
Scope and Contents
The records consist of song arrangements, sheet music, audio recordings, membership lists, advertisements, clippings, photographs, posters, scrapbooks, and other memorabilia of the Yale Whiffenpoofs.
Arrangement
The records are arranged by accession.
College students -- Societies, etc.; Students' songs; Vocal groups; Audiotapes; Photographs; Posters; Scrapbooks; Whiffenpoofs (Musical group); Yale University -- Songs and music; Yale University -- Societies, etc.; Yale University -- Students
- Members' lists, 1940-1954; Accession 19ND-A-485
  - Members' lists, 1940-1954 (Box 1)
- Advertisements, clippings and posters, 1983; Accession 1984-A-052
  - Advertisements, clippings and posters, 1983 (Box 1)
    - Oversized material (Box AF6)
- Scrapbook, 1950; Accession 1991-A-091
  Scope and Contents
  Recording of the 1950 Whiffenpoofs was transferred to the library"s Historical Sound Recordings collection.
  - Scrapbook, 1950 (Box 1)
- Reunion memorabilia, 1939-1990; Accession 1991-A-103
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted until Jan 1, 2025
  - 30th Reunion: Correspondence and Photographs, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Rudy Vallee, circa 1939-1949 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - 40th Reunion, 1949 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - 50th Reunion, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 60th Reunion, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Whiffs, 1970-1978 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - 70th Reunion, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Correspondence, 1980 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 75th Reunion, 1984 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Whiffs, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Women and the Whiffenpoofs, 1987-1988 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - 80th Reunion: Private party of 1945-1950 Whiffenpoonfs in Old Lyme. Taped and donated by J. Marshall, 1989; 1 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Correspondence, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - 1970 Whiffenpoofs 20th Reunion
    - [Branford College], 1990 June 1; videotape (VHS) (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Table Cards announcing concert. Donated by Richard Alfieri, "71, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Frisbees donated by Richard Alfieri, "71, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Clippings, 1946-1990 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Address Lists (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Song arrangements, circa 1946-1992; Accession 1994-A-001 (Box 1)
  No online inventory available. Paper inventory available in repository.
- "Songs of the Whiffenpoofs" manuscript, circa 1948; Accession 1994-A-084
  - "Songs of the Whiffenpoofs" manuscript, circa 1948 (Box 1)
- Records, photographs, and other material documenting the activities of the Whiffenpoofs, 1945-1994; Accession 1994-A-128
  - Blazer patch, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Biographical sketch and clipping, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - The Whiffenpoof Song (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Audition materials, 1986 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Portraits (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - 1945 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - 1947 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - 1948 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - 1949 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Materials from Button, Button, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Materials from Whoosh, 1948 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Alumni
    - Gentlemen Songsters, vol. 4, 1994 April (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Lower Potomac River Valley Ballad Singers (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Musikfest (Bethlehem, PA), 1992 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Original sheet music, Whiff arrangements, Whiff index, and ALS by C. Lohmann, circa 1904-1997; Accession 1998-A-099
  - Alexander (Box 1)
    Words by: Andrew Sterling
    Music by: Harry Von Tilzer
  - Alexander's Ragtime Band (Box 1)
    Words by: Irving Berlin
    Music by: Irving Berlin
  - All Coons Look Alike to Me (Box 3)
    Words by: Ernest Hogan
    Music by: Ernest Hogan
  - Bill Bailey, Won't You Please Come Home (Box 1)
    Words by: Hughie Cannon
    Music by: Hughie Cannon
  - Daddy is a Yale Man (Box 1)
    Words by: Dave Lippincott
    Music by: Dave Lippincott
  - Down Among the Shletering Pams (Box 1)
    Words by: James Brockman
    Music by: Abe Olman
  - Honey man (Box 3)
    Words by: Joe McCarthy
    Music by: Al Piantadosi
  - Hong Kong Blues (Box 1)
    Words by: Hoagy Carmichael
    Music by: Hoaqy Carmichael
  - How Long Has This Been Going On? (Box 1)
    Words by: Ira Gerswhin
    Music by: George Gershwin
  - How ya Gonna Keep 'em Down on the Farm (Box 1)
    Words by: Joe Young Sam Lewis
    Music by: Walter Donaldson
  - It Takes A Long Tall Brown-Skin Gal (Box 1)
    Words by: Marshall Walker
    Music by: Will E. Skidmore
  - I've Got A Feelin' For You (Box 3)
    Words by: Madden and Morse
    Music by: Madden & Morse
  - I've Got the Time-I've Got the Place (Box 3)
    Words by: Ballard MacDonald
    Music by: S. R. Henry
  - Jamboree Jones (Box 1)
    Words by: Johnny Mercer
    Music by: Johnny Mercer
  - Lora-Belle Lee (Box 1)
    Words by: Sid Miller and Ray Gilbert
    Music by: Sid Miller and Ray Gilbert
  - Macnamara's Band (Box 1)
    Words by: John J. Stamford
    Music by: Shamus O'Connor
  - Mandy (Box 1)
  - mandy Lee (Box 1)
    Words by: Thurland Chattaway
    Music by: Thurland Chattaway
  - Miss Otis Regrets (Box 1)
    Words by: Cole Porter
    Music by: Cole Porter
  - My Home Town Is A One Horse Town (Box 1)
    Words by: Alex Gerber
    Music by: Abner Silver
  - Oceana Roll (Box 1)
    Words by: Roger Lewis
    Music by: Lucien Denni
  - Oh By Jingo (Box 1)
    Words by: Lew Brown
    Music by: Albert Von Tilzer
  - Oh! By Jingo (Box 3)
    Words by: lewis Brown
  - One-Two-Three-Four (Box 1)
    Words by: S. Kamala
    Music by: Jack Alau
  - Passport Photograph (Box 1)
    Words by: Ray Perkins
    Music by: Ray Perkins
  - Put On Your Old Grey Bonnet (Box 3)
    Words by: Stanely Murphy
    Music by: Percy Wenrich
  - Put the Blame on Mame (Box 1)
    Words by: Allan Roberts, Doris Fisher
    Music by: Allan Roberts Doris Fisher
  - Ragtime Violin (Box 1)
  - Rose of Washington Square (Box 1)
    Music by: James F. Hanley
  - Saloon (Box 1)
    Words by: George Whiting
    Music by: Roland E. Llab
  - Some of These Days (Box 1)
    Words by: Shelton Brooks
    Music by: Shelton Brooks
  - Sunshine Girl (Box 1)
    Words by: Bob Merrill
    Music by: Bob Merrill
  - Tea for Two (Box 1)
    Words by: Caesar and Harbach
    Music by: Vincent Youmans
  - Teasing 1904 (Box 3)
    Words by: Cecil Mack
  - Teasing 1936 (Box 2)
  - The Ace Down in the Hole (Box 2)
    Words by: Jams Dempsey
    Music by: George Mitchell
  - The Gang That Sang 'Heart of My Heart' (Box 2)
    Words by: Ben Ryan
    Music by: Ben Ryan
  - The Memphis Blues (Box 2)
    Words by: George A. Norton
    Music by: W.C. Handy
  - The Pullman Porters on Parade (Box 2)
    Words by: Ben G. May
    Music by: Maurice Abrahms
  - The Whiffenpoof Song 1936 (Box 2)
    Words by: Meade Minnegerode George Pomeroy
    Music by: Todd Galloway
  - The Whiffenpoof Song 1944 (Box 2)
    Words by: Moss Hart
    Music by: Rudy Valee
  - There'll Be Some Changes Made (Box 2)
    Words by: Billy Higgins
    Music by: W. Benton Overstreet
  - Toot Toot Toosie (Goo'bya) (Box 2)
    Words by: Kahn, Erdman, Russo
    Music by: Kahn, Erdman, Russo
  - What You Goin' To Do When the Rent Comes Round? (Box 2)
  - When You Wore a Tulip (Box 2)
    Words by: Jack Mahoney
    Music by: Percy Wnrich
  - You Stepped Out of A Dream (Box 2)
    Words by: Gus Kahn
    Music by: Ncip Herb Brown
- Scrapbook, 1979; Accession 1999-A-085
  - Scrapbook, 1979 (Box 1)
- Sheet music and memorabilia, circa 1904-1994; Accession 2000-A-044
  - List of Ballads and Novelty Songs Series I by Harry Von Tilzer (Box 1)
  - List of Novelty Songs Series II and Instrumental Numbers by Harry Von Tilzef (Box 1)
  - Picture of the 1923 Whiffenpoofs on the Fence (Box 1)
  - Yale Record (centerfold copy of Lippencott's "Daddy Is A Yale Man"), 1946 October 10 (Box 1)
  - The Whiffenpoofs of Yale University Eighty-Fifth Anniversary 1909-1994 (booklet) (Box 1)
  - The Yale Whiffenpoofs Weekend Program 85th Anniversary Reunion, 1994 (Box 1)
  - Letter from Kent Sanger to Prof. Collins with words to "The Yale Song", 1986 August 27 (Box 1)
  - Letter from Wally Collins to Kent Sanger re the Aug 27, 1986 letter, 1986 October 13 (Box 1)
  - Sheet Music
    - Collegiate; Moe Jaffe and Nat Bonx (words and music) (Box 1)
    - Down In Jungle Town; Edward Madden (words), Theodore Morse (music) (Box 1)
    - I Married the bootlegger"s Daughter; Frank Crumit (words and music) (Box 1)
    - Lazy River; DeVol, Manley, Mecum (words and music) (Box 1)
    - Louisville Lou; Jack Yellen (words), Milton Ager (music) (Box 1)
    - Lulu's Back In Town; Al Dubin (words), Harry Warren (music) (Box 1)
    - My Cutie's Due at Two-to-Two; Robin and Von Tilzer (words and music) (Box 1)
    - Pullman Porters Parade; Ren. G. May (words), Maurice Abrahams (music) (Box 1)
    - Strike Up the Band Here Comes the Sailor; Andrew Sterling (words), Chas. B. Ward (music) (Box 1)
    - There'll Be Some Changes Made; Billy Higgins (words), W. Benton Overstreet (music) (Box 1)
    - Wedding Bells (Are Breaking Up That Old Gang of Mine); Raskin and Kanal (words), Fain (music) (Box 1)
    - A Nightingale Sang in Berkeley Square; Eric Maschwitz (words), Manning Sherwin (music) (Box 1)
    - Without A Song; William Rose and Edward Eliscu (words), Vincent Youmans (music) (Box 1)
    - Sit Down You're Rockin' the Boat; Frank Loesser (Box 1)
- Poster for Whiffenpoofs Jamboree, 1967; Accession 2001-A-109
  - Poster for Whiffenpoofs Jamboree, 1967 (Box 1)
- Poster, circa 2000; Accession 2001-A-126
  - Poster, circa 2000 (Box 1)
- Photograph album, 1965; Accession 2003-A-094
  - Photograph album, 1965 (Box 1)
- "Whiffenpoofs in China"; Scrapbook, 1986, 1957; Accession 2003-A-100
  - "Whiffenpoofs in China", 1986; videotape (VHS) (Box 1U)
  - Scrapbook, 1957 (Box 2)
- Scrapbooks, 1946-1947, 1954-1955; Accession 2003-A-126
  - Scrapbooks, 1946-1955 (Box 1)
- "Perfect Harmony: The Whiffenpoofs in China", 1985; Accession 2004-A-038
  - "Perfect Harmony: The Whiffenpoofs in China", 1985; 1 (Box 1)
    Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy of non-commercially produced items for their personal use should consult the ordering reproductions information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
- Scrapbook, 1948; Accession 2005-A-123
  - Scrapbook, 1948 (Box 1)
- Anniversary ephemera, 1985-1989; Accession 2008-A-072
  - 75th anniversary brochure, 1985 (Box 1)
  - 80th anniversary
    - Reunion weekend program, 1989
    - Reunion weekend songbook, 1989
    - Saturday evening program, 1989
- Scrapbook, 1972; Accession 2008-A-178 (Box 1)
- Whiffenpoofs centennial poster, 2009; Accession 2009-A-211
  The materials are open for research.
  - Whiffenpoofs centennial poster, 2009 (Box 1)